# Joshua E. Lambert, Ph.D.

🔇 jelambert.com 🔀 joshuae.lambert@gmail.com in in/joshuaelambert/ 💆 twitter.com/jelambert\_

### ABOUT

I am a recently defended Ph.D. skilled in computational social science methods. I have experience with econometric methods, natural language processing, machine learning, and geospatial analysis. I have published popular and scholarly work that has looked at various conflict dynamics, political instability, and leader psychology utilizing both qualitative and quantitative methods.

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D.. Security Studies

University of Central Florida, Orlando, FL, August 2020

"Food, Familiarity, and Forecasting: Modeling Coups with Computational Methods"

M.A., Political Science

University of New Orleans, New Orleans, LA, December 2015

Concentration: International Relations

B.A., Political Science

Auburn University, Auburn, AL, May 2014

Minor: Religious Studies

### WORK EXPERIENCE

### **NLP/Machine Learning Researcher** (Part time)

August 2020 - Present

National Center for Integrated Coastal Research - UCF, Orlando, FL

- NLP research regarding topical trends in the field of collective resource usage and man-
- Development of supervised machine learning systems to classify common resources out-

## Graduate Research Associate (Part time)

January 2020 - August 2020

Kurdish Political Studies Program - UCF, Orlando, FL

- Data management and analysis.
  - KPSP speakers, scholarship and event logistical support.

#### Adjunct Lecturer (Part time)

August 2019 - May 2020

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs - UCF, Orlando, FL

POS 4764 - GIS for Political Analysis, Jupyter notebook repository

Graduate Research Associate (Part time)

May 2018 - July 2019

Intelligence Community's Center for Academic Excellence - UCF, Orlando, FL

- Design and development of data website: Psychological Characteristics of Leaders (PsyCL)
- Managed RA team collection of longitudinal, cross-national leader speech materials.

### Researcher (Full time)

May 2018 - August 2018

Secure Fisheries - One Earth Future, Broomfield, CO

- Collaboration on the design and implementation of the Fisheries Conflict Database.
- Conduct machine coding, database management, data collection, processing and analysis.

## Visiting Research Fellow (Part time)

August 2017 - May 2018

Intelligence Community's Center for Academic Excellence - UCF, Orlando, FL

· Generate coding schemes for societal source material from 1950-2004, and oversee collection. Conduct data visualization and statistical analysis.

## Graduate Teaching Assistant (Part time)

August 2016 - May 2018

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs - UCF, Orlando, FL

• International Relations, Comparative Politics, Geography, Political Science, Public Policy

### Research Assistant (Part time)

August 2013 - May 2014

Department of Political Science - AU, Auburn, AL

Developed coding scheme and coded over 850 news articles to determine media perception of D.C. Mayor Marion Barry. Analyzed quantitative and qualitative data.

# COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming: Python, SQL, ArcGIS, R, Stata
Data Science: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Jupyter, Scikit-learn, NLTK, GeoPandas

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- 2021 "Presidential Personalities and Operational Codes: Learning Effects and Midterm Congressional Election Results" Book Chapter in Operational Code Analysis and Foreign Policy Roles Crossing Simon's Bridge (2020) Joshua E. Lambert, Mark Schafer, Stephen Walker, and Collin Kazazis.
- 2020 "Introducing the Commons Synthesis Project: Topics and trends in the study of common-pool resource" *Under Review* (2020) Joshua E. Lambert, Graham Epstein, Jennifer Joel, and Jacopo Baggio.
- 2020 "The Causes and Consequences of Fisheries Conflict around the Horn of Africa" Under Review (2020) Sarah M. Glaser, Colleen Devlin, Joshua E. Lambert, and Ciera Villegas.
- 2020 "Psychological Characteristics of Leaders (PsyCL): Introducing a New Data Set" *Under Review* (2020) Mark Schafer and **Joshua E. Lambert**.
- 2019 "Reassessing Private Military and Security Company(PMSC) 'Competition' in Civil War: Lessons from Sierra Leone" Small Wars and Insurgencies. (2019) Christopher M. Faulkner, Joshua E. Lambert, and Jonathan Powell.
- 2019 "Reassessing Rebellion" One Earth Future. Eric Keels, Jay Benson, John Filitz, and Joshua E. Lambert.
- 2019 "Why Sudan's deadly crackdown on protesters could escalate in coming weeks"

  The Conversation. Eric Keels and Joshua E. Lambert.
- 2019 "Peeling back the layers on the role of private security companies in Africa"

  The Conversation. Christopher Faulkner, Joshua E. Lambert, and Jonathan Powell.
- 2018 "Fish Wars: The Causes and Consequences of Fisheries Conflict in Tanzania" One Earth Future. Sarah M. Glaser, Colleen Devlin, Joshua E. Lambert, Ciera Villegas, and Natasia Poinsatte.
- 2018 "Rulers, Elections, and Irregular Governance (REIGN) Showcase: Part I" One Earth Future. Clayton Besaw, Joshua E. Lambert, and Jean-Pierre Larroque.

### WORKING PAPERS

"Global Patterns in Religion and Large Scale Violence" (With Güneş Murat Tezcür)

"Coup-Proofing, Mutinies, and Private Military and Security Companies" (with Christopher Faulkner)

"Them Belly Full but We Hungry: Food Insecurity as an Elite Motivator for Coups"

# CONFERENCE PARTICIPATION

- 2020 International Studies Association (Cancelled Honolulu, HI)
- 2019 International Studies Association (Toronto, CAN)
- 2018 Southern Political Science Association (New Orleans, LA)
- Florida Political Science Association (Orlando, FL); Southwestern Political Science Association (Austin, TX); International Society of Political Psychology Association (Edinburgh, SCT); International Studies Association South (Orlando, FL)

	Alabama Political Science Association (Montgomery, AL); Southern Political Science Association (New Orleans, LA)	
	2013 Alabama Political Science Association (Tuscaloosa, AL)	
RESEARCH INTERESTS	Conflict, Environmental Security, Civil-Military Relations, Political Psychology, Data Mining, Remote Sensing, Forecasting	
SERVICE	President - Political Science Graduate Student Association (UCF)	2018 - 2019
	Vice President - Student Government Association (UNO)	2015
	Member - Dean Search Committee (UNO)	2015
	Senator - Student Government Association (UNO)	2014 - 2015
AWARDS &	2020 ViEWS Conflict Forecasting Competition invited participant	Uppsala, SWE
PROFESSIONAL	2018 PRIO Conflict Trends Course participant	Oslo, NOR
DEVELOPMENT	2018 SciPy conference workshop participant	Austin, TX
	2017 GEOINT Symposium participant	Tampa Bay, FL
	2017 DIA Summer Seminar participant	Washington D.C.
	2017 UCF Political Science Colloquium presenter	Orlando, FL
	2017 Florida Political Science Graduate Paper Winner	Orlando, FL
	2017 ISPP Summer Methodology Academy participant	Edinburgh, SCT
	2015 UNO Student Government Senator of the year	New Orleans, LA

# Jonathan Powell | Committee Chair

Associate Professor

REFERENCES

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida Jonathan.Powell@ucf.edu

407-823-2082

# Konstantin Ash | Committee Co-Chair

Assistant Professor

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida Konstantin.Ash@ucf.edu 407-823-2608

# **Peter Jacques** | Committee Member

Professor

School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs

University of Central Florida

Peter.Jacques@ucf.edu

407-823-6773

# Güneş Murat Tezcür | Supervisor

Professor and Jalal Talabani Chair of Kurdish Political Studies School of Politics, Security, and International Affairs University of Central Florida Tezcur@ucf.edu 407-823-2040